<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cofactors on Erick Armingol</title>
    <link>https://earmingol.github.io/tags/cofactors/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cofactors on Erick Armingol</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://earmingol.github.io/tags/cofactors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the impact of the cofactor swapping of isocitrate dehydrogenase over the growth phenotype of Escherichia coli on acetate by using constraint-based modeling</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/ecoli-fba/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/ecoli-fba/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been proposed that NADP+-specificity of isocitrate dehydrogenase (ICDH)&#xA;evolved as an adaptation of microorganisms to grow on acetate as the sole&#xA;source of carbon and energy. In Escherichia coli, changing the cofactor&#xA;specificity of ICDH from NADP+ to NAD+ (cofactor swapping) decreases the&#xA;growth rate on acetate. However, the metabolic basis of this phenotype has&#xA;not been analyzed. In this work, we used constraint-based modeling to&#xA;investigate the effect of the cofactor swapping of ICDH in terms of energy&#xA;production, response of alternative sources of NADPH, and partitioning of&#xA;fluxes between ICDH and isocitrate lyase (ICL) -a crucial bifurcation when&#xA;the bacterium grows on acetate-. We generated E. coli strains expressing&#xA;NAD+-specific ICDH instead of the native enzyme, and bearing the deletion&#xA;of the NADPH-producing transhydrogenase PntAB. We measured their growth rate&#xA;and acetate uptake rate, modeled the distribution of metabolic fluxes by Flux&#xA;Balance Analysis (FBA), and quantified the specific activities of&#xA;NADPH-producing dehydrogenases in central pathways. The cofactor swapping&#xA;of ICDH led to one-third decrease in biomass yield, irrespective of the&#xA;presence of PntAB. According to our simulations, the diminution in growth&#xA;rate observed upon cofactor swapping could be explained by one-half decrease&#xA;in the total production of NADPH and a lower availability of carbon for&#xA;biosynthesis because of a change in the partition at the isocitrate&#xA;bifurcation. Together with an increased total ATP production, this scenario&#xA;resulted in a 10-fold increment in the flux of ATP not used for growing&#xA;purposes. PntAB was identified as the primary NADPH balancing response,&#xA;with the dehydrogenases of the oxidative branch of the Pentose Phosphate&#xA;Pathway and the malic enzyme playing a role in its absence. We propose that&#xA;in the context of E. coli growing on acetate, the NADP+-specificity of ICDH&#xA;is a trait that impacts not only NADPH production, but also the efficient&#xA;allocation of carbon and energy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
