<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cell-Cell Communication on Erick Armingol</title>
    <link>https://earmingol.github.io/tags/cell-cell-communication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cell-Cell Communication on Erick Armingol</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://earmingol.github.io/tags/cell-cell-communication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Computational suite for studying cell-cell interactions and communication</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/projects/software/cell2cell/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/projects/software/cell2cell/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pypi.org/project/cell2cell/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://badge.fury.io/py/cell2cell.svg&#34; alt=&#34;PyPI Version&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-suite-cell2cell-includes-two-main-sub-tools&#34;&gt;The suite &lt;em&gt;cell2cell&lt;/em&gt; includes two main sub-tools:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The regular cell2cell, which includes the main approaches described in our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41576-020-00292-x&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tensor-cell2cell, a novel method that uses tensor factorization to deconvolve&#xA;patterns of cell-cell communication across multiple cellular contexts&#xA;(e.g., time points, disease states, cellular location, patients, etc.), as described&#xA;in our &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-31369-2&#34;&gt;research article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;tutorials&#34;&gt;Tutorials&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;cell2cell-examples&#34;&gt;cell2cell Examples&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/earmingol/cell2cell/blob/master/Logo.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;cell2cell Logo&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/earmingol/cell2cell/blob/master/examples/cell2cell/Toy-Example.ipynb&#34;&gt;Step-by-step Pipeline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://earmingol.github.io/cell2cell/tutorials/Toy-Example-BulkPipeline&#34;&gt;Interaction Pipeline for Bulk Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://earmingol.github.io/cell2cell/tutorials/Toy-Example-SingleCellPipeline&#34;&gt;Interaction Pipeline for Single-Cell Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/LewisLabUCSD/Celegans-cell2cell&#34;&gt;Whole Body of &lt;em&gt;C. elegans&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;tensor-cell2cell-examples&#34;&gt;Tensor-cell2cell Examples&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/earmingol/cell2cell/blob/master/LogoTensor.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;Tensor-cell2cell Logo&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metabolic activity from single‑cell and spatial transcriptomics with scCellFie</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/projects/software/sccellfie/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/projects/software/sccellfie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pypi.org/project/sccellfie/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://badge.fury.io/py/sccellfie.svg&#34; alt=&#34;PyPI&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://codecov.io/gh/earmingol/scCellFie&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://codecov.io/gh/earmingol/scCellFie/graph/badge.svg?token=22NENAKNKI&#34; alt=&#34;Codecov&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pepy.tech/project/sccellfie&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pepy.tech/badge/sccellfie/month&#34; alt=&#34;Downloads&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.shields.io/badge/License-MIT-yellow.svg&#34; alt=&#34;License: MIT&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;metabolic-activity-from-singlecell-and-spatial-transcriptomics-with-sccellfie&#34;&gt;Metabolic activity from single‑cell and spatial transcriptomics with &lt;strong&gt;scCellFie&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;scCellFie&lt;/strong&gt; is a Python‑based tool for analyzing metabolic activity at different resolutions, developed at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ventolab.org/&#34;&gt;Vento Lab&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;It efficiently processes both single‑cell and spatial data to predict metabolic task activities.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;While its prediction strategy is inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/LewisLabUCSD/CellFie&#34;&gt;CellFie&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lewislab.ucsd.edu/&#34;&gt;Lewis Lab&lt;/a&gt; (originally in MATLAB for bulk and small single‑cell datasets), &lt;strong&gt;scCellFie&lt;/strong&gt; adds multiple improvements such as marker selection, differential analysis, and cell‑cell communication inference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atlas-scale metabolic activities inferred from single-cell and spatial transcriptomics</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/sccellfie/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/sccellfie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Metabolism supplies energy, building blocks, and signaling molecules vital for&#xA;cell function and communication, but methods to directly measure it at single-cell&#xA;and/or spatial resolutions remain technically challenging and inaccessible for most&#xA;researchers. Single-cell and spatial transcriptomics offer high-throughput data alternatives&#xA;with a rich ecosystem of computational tools. Here, we present scCellFie, a computational&#xA;framework to infer metabolic activities from human and mouse transcriptomic data at&#xA;single-cell and spatial resolution. Applied to ∼30 million cell profiles, we generated&#xA;a comprehensive metabolic atlas across human organs, identifying organ– and&#xA;cell-type-specific activities. In the endometrium, scCellFie reveals metabolic&#xA;programs contributing to healthy tissue remodeling during the menstrual cycle, with&#xA;temporal patterns replicated in data from in vitro cultures. We also uncover&#xA;disease-associated metabolic alterations in endometriosis and endometrial carcinoma,&#xA;linked to proinflammatory macrophages, and metabolite-mediated epithelial cell&#xA;communication, respectively. Ultimately, scCellFie provides a scalable toolbox for&#xA;extracting interpretable metabolic functionalities from transcriptomic data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The diversification of methods for studying cell–cell interactions and communication</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/cci-reviewv2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/cci-reviewv2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;No cell lives in a vacuum, and the molecular interactions between cells define most phenotypes.&#xA;Transcriptomics provides rich information to infer cell–cell interactions and communication,&#xA;thus accelerating the discovery of the roles of cells within their communities. Such research&#xA;relies heavily on algorithms that infer which cells are interacting and the ligands and receptors&#xA;involved. Specific pressures on different research niches are driving the evolution of next-generation&#xA;computational tools, enabling new conceptual opportunities and technological advances.&#xA;More sophisticated algorithms now account for the heterogeneity and spatial organization of&#xA;cells, multiple ligand types and intracellular signalling events, and enable the use of larger&#xA;and more complex datasets, including single-cell and spatial transcriptomics. Similarly,&#xA;new high-throughput experimental methods are increasing the number and resolution of interactions&#xA;that can be analysed simultaneously. Here, we explore recent progress in cell–cell interaction&#xA;research and highlight the diversification of the next generation of tools, which have yielded&#xA;a rich ecosystem of tools for different applications and are enabling invaluable discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inferring a spatial code of cell-cell interactions across a whole animal body</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/cci-celegans/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/cci-celegans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cell-cell interactions shape cellular function and ultimately organismal&#xA;phenotype. Interacting cells can sense their mutual distance using&#xA;combinations of ligand-receptor pairs, suggesting the existence of a&#xA;spatial code, i.e., signals encoding spatial properties of cellular&#xA;organization. However, this code driving and sustaining the spatial&#xA;organization of cells remains to be elucidated. Here we present a&#xA;computational framework to infer the spatial code underlying cell-cell&#xA;interactions from the transcriptomes of the cell types across the whole&#xA;body of a multicellular organism. As core of this framework, we introduce&#xA;our tool cell2cell, which uses the coexpression of ligand-receptor pairs&#xA;to compute the potential for intercellular interactions, and we test it&#xA;across the Caenorhabditis elegans’ body. Leveraging a 3D atlas of&#xA;C. elegans’ cells, we also implement a genetic algorithm to identify the&#xA;ligand-receptor pairs most informative of the spatial organization of&#xA;cells across the whole body. Validating the spatial code extracted with&#xA;this strategy, the resulting intercellular distances are negatively&#xA;correlated with the inferred cell-cell interactions. Furthermore, for&#xA;selected cell-cell and ligand-receptor pairs, we experimentally confirm&#xA;the communicatory behavior inferred with cell2cell and the genetic&#xA;algorithm. Thus, our framework helps identify a code that predicts the&#xA;spatial organization of cells across a whole-animal body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Context-aware deconvolution of cell-cell communication with Tensor-cell2cell</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/tensor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/tensor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cell interactions determine phenotypes, and intercellular communication is shaped by cellular contexts such as disease&#xA;state, organismal life stage, and tissue microenvironment. Single-cell technologies measure the molecules mediating&#xA;cell–cell communication, and emerging computational tools can exploit these data to decipher intercellular communication.&#xA;However, current methods either disregard cellular context or rely on simple pairwise comparisons between samples,&#xA;thus limiting the ability to decipher complex cell–cell communication across multiple time points, levels of disease&#xA;severity, or spatial contexts. Here we present Tensor-cell2cell, an unsupervised method using tensor decomposition,&#xA;which deciphers context-driven intercellular communication by simultaneously accounting for multiple stages, states,&#xA;or locations of the cells. To do so, Tensor-cell2cell uncovers context-driven patterns of communication associated&#xA;with different phenotypic states and determined by unique combinations of cell types and ligand-receptor pairs.&#xA;As such, Tensor-cell2cell robustly improves upon and extends the analytical capabilities of existing tools.&#xA;We show Tensor-cell2cell can identify multiple modules associated with distinct communication processes (e.g.,&#xA;participating cell–cell and ligand-receptor pairs) linked to severities of Coronavirus Disease 2019 and to Autism&#xA;Spectrum Disorder. Thus, we introduce an effective and easy-to-use strategy for understanding complex communication&#xA;patterns across diverse conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor-cell2cell: Desde la transcriptómica a entender cómo el contexto biológico afecta la comunicación intercelular</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/accdis-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/accdis-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Talk given in the ACCDiS Seminars about single-cell transcriptomics applied to understand chronic diseases&#xA;&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yj_OLscLFC0?autoplay=1&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=1&amp;amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computational resources for studying cell-cell communication</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/hca-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/hca-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Talk given in the workshop about single-cell RNA-seq organized by the Human Cell Atlas for the Latin American community.&#xA;This talk can be found at the time 1:01:42.&#xA;&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/fOEWkVf2vk0?t=3702?autoplay=1&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=1&amp;amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering cell-cell interactions and communication from gene expression</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/cci-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/cci-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cell–cell interactions orchestrate organismal development, homeostasis and&#xA;single-cell functions. When cells do not properly interact or improperly&#xA;decode molecular messages, disease ensues. Thus, the identification and&#xA;quantification of intercellular signalling pathways has become a common&#xA;analysis performed across diverse disciplines. The expansion of protein–protein&#xA;interaction databases and recent advances in RNA sequencing technologies have&#xA;enabled routine analyses of intercellular signalling from gene expression&#xA;measurements of bulk and single-cell data sets. In particular, ligand–receptor&#xA;pairs can be used to infer intercellular communication from the coordinated&#xA;expression of their cognate genes. In this Review, we highlight discoveries&#xA;enabled by analyses of cell–cell interactions from transcriptomic data and&#xA;review the methods and tools used in this context.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cell-cell interactions and communication</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/projects/research/ccis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/projects/research/ccis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In multicellular organisms, high-order organizations of cells are defined by&#xA;their cell-cell interactions (CCIs). Cells constantly sense their&#xA;microenvironment and can trigger intracellular changes depending on the&#xA;information that they receive. These communicatory processes allow single&#xA;cells to coordinate their gene expression, which further enables the&#xA;coordination of a collective behavior of cells. Thus, functions and&#xA;phenotypes of multicellular organizations are orchestrated by their CCIs. The&#xA;main focus of my research is on generating novel approaches to infer CCIs to&#xA;help decipher how phenotypes are associated and how they depend on these&#xA;processes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
