<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>High-Throughput Experiments on Erick Armingol</title>
    <link>https://earmingol.github.io/tags/high-throughput-experiments/</link>
    <description>Recent content in High-Throughput Experiments on Erick Armingol</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://earmingol.github.io/tags/high-throughput-experiments/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The diversification of methods for studying cell–cell interactions and communication</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/cci-reviewv2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/cci-reviewv2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;No cell lives in a vacuum, and the molecular interactions between cells define most phenotypes.&#xA;Transcriptomics provides rich information to infer cell–cell interactions and communication,&#xA;thus accelerating the discovery of the roles of cells within their communities. Such research&#xA;relies heavily on algorithms that infer which cells are interacting and the ligands and receptors&#xA;involved. Specific pressures on different research niches are driving the evolution of next-generation&#xA;computational tools, enabling new conceptual opportunities and technological advances.&#xA;More sophisticated algorithms now account for the heterogeneity and spatial organization of&#xA;cells, multiple ligand types and intracellular signalling events, and enable the use of larger&#xA;and more complex datasets, including single-cell and spatial transcriptomics. Similarly,&#xA;new high-throughput experimental methods are increasing the number and resolution of interactions&#xA;that can be analysed simultaneously. Here, we explore recent progress in cell–cell interaction&#xA;research and highlight the diversification of the next generation of tools, which have yielded&#xA;a rich ecosystem of tools for different applications and are enabling invaluable discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
