<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>single-cell on Erick Armingol</title>
    <link>https://earmingol.github.io/tags/single-cell/</link>
    <description>Recent content in single-cell on Erick Armingol</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://earmingol.github.io/tags/single-cell/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Computational suite for studying cell-cell interactions and communication</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/projects/software/cell2cell/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/projects/software/cell2cell/</guid>
      <description>The suite cell2cell includes two main sub-tools:
 The regular cell2cell, which includes the main approaches described in our review. Tensor-cell2cell, a novel method that uses tensor factorization to deconvolve patterns of cell-cell communication across multiple cellular contexts (e.g., time points, disease states, cellular location, patients, etc.), as described in our pre-print.    A toy example using the under-the-hood methods of cell2cell is available here. This case allows personalizing the analyses in a higher level, but it may result harder to use.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker container for single-cell analyses</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/projects/software/sc-docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/projects/software/sc-docker/</guid>
      <description>This Docker container includes:
 Anaconda &amp;amp; Jupyter Python 3.8.8 scanpy cell2cell R 4.0.3 Seurat SeuratDisk Harmony CellChat  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Context-aware deconvolution of cell-cell communication with Tensor-cell2cell</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/tensor/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/tensor/</guid>
      <description>Cell interactions determine phenotypes, and intercellular communication is shaped by cellular contexts such as disease state, organismal life stage, and tissue microenvironment. Single-cell technologies measure the molecules mediating cell-cell communication, and emerging computational tools can exploit these data to decipher intercellular communication. However, current methods either disregard cellular context or rely on simple pairwise comparisons between samples, thus limiting the ability to decipher complex cell-cell communication across multiple time points, levels of disease severity, or spatial contexts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tensor-cell2cell: Desde la transcriptómica a entender cómo el contexto biológico afecta la comunicación intercelular</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/accdis-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/accdis-talk/</guid>
      <description>Talk given in the ACCDiS Seminars about single-cell transcriptomics applied to understand chronic diseases   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational resources for studying cell-cell communication</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/hca-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/hca-talk/</guid>
      <description>Talk given in the workshop about single-cell RNA-seq organized by the Human Cell Atlas for the Latin American community. This talk can be found at the time 1:01:42.   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inferring a spatial code of cell-cell interactions across a whole animal body</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/cci-celegans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/cci-celegans/</guid>
      <description>Cell-cell interactions shape cellular function and ultimately organismal phenotype. However, the spatial code embedded in the molecular interactions driving and sustaining spatial organization remains to be elucidated. Here we present a computational framework to infer the spatial code underlying cell-cell interactions in a whole animal. Using the transcriptomes of the cell types composing Caenorhabditis elegans’ body, we compute the potential for intercellular interactions from the coexpression of ligand-receptor pairs. Leveraging a 3D atlas of C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering cell-cell interactions and communication from gene expression</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/cci-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/publications/cci-review/</guid>
      <description>Cell–cell interactions orchestrate organismal development, homeostasis and single-cell functions. When cells do not properly interact or improperly decode molecular messages, disease ensues. Thus, the identification and quantification of intercellular signalling pathways has become a common analysis performed across diverse disciplines. The expansion of protein–protein interaction databases and recent advances in RNA sequencing technologies have enabled routine analyses of intercellular signalling from gene expression measurements of bulk and single-cell data sets. In particular, ligand–receptor pairs can be used to infer intercellular communication from the coordinated expression of their cognate genes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cell-cell interactions and communication</title>
      <link>https://earmingol.github.io/projects/research/ccis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://earmingol.github.io/projects/research/ccis/</guid>
      <description>In multicellular organisms, high-order organizations of cells are defined by their cell-cell interactions (CCIs). Cells constantly sense their microenvironment and can trigger intracellular changes depending on the information that they receive. These communicatory processes allow single cells to coordinate their gene expression, which further enables the coordination of a collective behavior of cells. Thus, functions and phenotypes of multicellular organizations are orchestrated by their CCIs. The main focus of my research is on generating novel approaches to infer CCIs to help decipher how phenotypes are associated and how they depend on these processes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
